Guide to the John Bain "Jock" Sutherland Collection, 1917-1961 UA.91.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
John Bain "Jock" Sutherland Collection
1917-1961
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Sutherland family
UA.91.2
4.29 Linear Feet (2 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes)
John Bain "Jock" Sutherland served as the head football coach for the University of Pittsburgh from 1924 to 1939. This collection contains correspondence related to his resignation as coach on March 4, 1939, as well as some material focusing on the time both before and after his resignation. It also includes some press materials and personal photographs of Sutherland, as well as materials published posthumously.
Biography
John Bain "Jock" Sutherland was the head coach of the Pitt Panthers football team for fifteen years, from 1924 to 1939. He was born March 21, 1889, in Coupar Angus, Scotland, and arrived in Pittsburgh in 1907. He worked at Dixmont Hospital while taking night classes at the YMCA and later attended the Oberlin Academy in Oberlin, OH, to prepare him for college courses. In 1914, he was admitted to the University of Pittsburgh to study dentistry.
In his first year of school, Sutherland joined the football team despite reportedly never playing the game before. Under coach Glenn "Pop" Warner, Sutherland demonstrated a great skill for the sport. During his time as a player, the Pitt football team lost only one game. Pitt claims two national championships from the time Sutherland was a student: 1915 and 1916. The 1917 team, sometimes called the Fighting Dentists for the number of dental students playing, was also extremely successful.
After graduating, Sutherland became the head coach of the Lafayette College football team from 1919 to 1923. He returned to Pitt in 1924 when Warner left to coach at Stanford. In addition to serving as the head football coach, Sutherland also served as a professor in the School of Dentistry. During this time, his teams produced a number of All-Americans and future College Football Hall of Famers, including Marshall Goldberg, Joe Donchess, Averell Daniel, and many others. Pitt also claims five national championships from Sutherland's time as coach: 1929, 1931, 1934, 1936, and 1937.
Toward the end of his time at Pitt, Sutherland found himself at odds with the university's administrators, including Chancellor John G. Bowman, who wanted to lessen the focus on athletics. As a result, a new set of guidelines for athletics was developed which stated, among other things, that the school would not recruit students to play sports. There was also contention over whether the school should provide financial support to the athletes. Unhappy with these decisions, Sutherland resigned from the University of Pittsburgh on March 4, 1939.
After ending a 25-year association with the university where he had been a player, student, professor, and coach, Sutherland took his talents to professional football. He became the coach of the Brooklyn Dodgers football team in 1940, where he found minor success. He left the Dodgers to join the Navy during World War II, despite being 53 years old at the time. After the war ended he joined the Pittsburgh Steelers as a coach, leading the team to some success. While on a scouting trip for the Steelers, Sutherland was diagnosed with a brain tumor after being found wandering along the side of a road in Kentucky. An attempt by surgeons in Pittsburgh to remove the tumor was unsuccessful, and he died on April 11, 1948.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into four series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Football
Series III. Press
Series IV. Personal
Scope and Content Notes
The collection focuses mainly on Jock Sutherland's resignation as head football coach of the University of Pittsburgh on March 4, 1939. Correspondence both to and from Sutherland documents the public reaction to his departure, as well as some personal asides on his part. There are also various momentos of that time, including resolutions from Pitt Clubs and a notice regarding student support for the coach. There are also records relating to the time before and after his resignation, and a focus on Sutherland's overall career as a coach, including magazine and newspaper articles and practice materials. The Sutherland Collection also includes photographs of Jock Sutherland, event programs, and a manuscript copy of Harry Scott's posthumous biography of the coach.
Acquisition Information
Purchased by the University of Pittsburgh's Archives & Special Collections in March 2018.
Custodial History
The materials in the collection were originally owned by the Sutherland family and were later given to the daughter of Eddie Schultz, a former player and assistant coach for Sutherland and a family friend. The collection was later acquired by Dan Means and then by the University of Pittsburgh's Archives & Special Collections.
Related Material
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, John Gabbert Bowman, Administrative Files, 1921-1945, UA.2.10.1921-1945, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
University of Pittsburgh; Correspondence; Football coaches -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; College sports; College athletes; Weber, John; Parcell, Malcolm; Carlson, Henry Clifford; Lafayette College (Easton, Pa.); Toomey, Regis; Rowswell, Albert Kennedy; Pitt Panthers (Football team); University of Pittsburgh; Bowman, John G. (John Gabbert); Sutherland, John Bain
- Correspondence, 1917-1941; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The correspondence in the collection focuses on Jock Sutherland's resignation as head football coach of the University of Pittsburgh. The bulk of the material documents reactions to Sutherland leaving the university, as well as his responses to each letter. There is also correspondence from before his resignation, including two letters written to Sutherland as a student. Also included is correspondence between Sutherland, Chancellor John G. Bowman, and other university officials documenting the build-up to Sutherland's resignation. All correspondence in the collection comes from a scrapbook, which due to preservation concerns was disbound and the documents removed from the book where possible. In the cases where a document could not be removed, photocopies were made and the location of the original was written on the back. The photocopies were then filed in the document's correct chronological location. All correspondence has been filed chronologically with some letters singled out due to the importance of the sender. The scrapbook also contained memorabilia, which has been placed together at the end of this series to preserve the provenance of the material.
  - Pre-Resignation Correspondence, 1917-1939; 1.
    The material in this subseries accounts for all correspondence in the collection from the time before Jock Sutherland's resignation from the University of Pittsburgh. It includes letters written to Sutherland as a student, including one from then-chancellor Samuel McCormick. It also includes letters written during or about football seasons, such as the letters discussing the 1937 victory over Nebraska from Dana Bible, then-athletic director of Nebraska, and Biff Jones, the coach of the Nebraska team. The correspondence from Pitt personnel includes some telegrams sent in support of Sutherland during earlier tensions with the university's administration and Sutherland's opinions on Athletic Council decisions.
    - Letters to Sutherland as a student, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter from Lafayette College student council, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John G. Bowman, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dana X. Bible, February 6, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lawrence McCeney "Biff" Jones, November 17, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pitt personnel, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Resignation Statement and Correspondence, 1939; 2.
    In this subseries, the material focuses on Jock Sutherland's resignation from the University of Pittsburgh on March 4, 1939. Included here is a copy of Sutherland's statement on his resignation, as well as correspondence reacting to it. The letters to Sutherland include those written by friends, colleagues, current and former players, and general fans. Sutherland's responses are included. There is also a note from the Pitt chapter of the American Student Union announcing support for their coach. Several well-known people wrote to Sutherland at this time, including actor and fellow Pitt alumnus Regis Toomey, Pittsburgh Pirates announcer Albert "Rosey" Rowswell, future legislator Eugene Caputo, and Harold A. Bruce, coach of the Austrian National Track Team. The correspondence also includes telegrams of encouragment for Sutherland from former players and colleagues such as Marshall Goldberg, Frank Walton, Joe Donchess, and Herb McCracken, among others.
    - Sutherland resignation statement, March 4, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - John G. Bowman, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harold Bruce, March 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Eugene Caputo, March 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Albert "Rosey" Rowswell, March 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Regis Toomey, March 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Pitt personnel, March 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - General, March-April 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Outside schools and athletic organizations, March-April 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Post-Resignation Correspondence, 1939-1941; 3.
    The correspondence in this subseries focuses on the time after Sutherland's resignation and is mostly unrelated to the resignation itself. It contains correspondence on several subjects, including job offers and requests for advice on hiring, the potential Sutherland Room in the Cathedral of Learning, post-resignation events, and congratulatory messages sent to Sutherland. Included also are telegrams from Marshall Goldberg, former Pittsburgh Pirates managers Pie Traynor and Jewel Ens, writers Frank Graham and Les Biederman, restaurateur Toots Shor, and many more regarding topics such as an April 1939 testimonial dinner, Sutherland's hiring as coach of the Brooklyn Dodgers, and simple birthday wishes. There are letters both to and from Sutherland, including one written to Bill Stern of the National Broadcasting Company regarding a radio broadcast, and a letter to the Erie Dispatch-Herald where Sutherland describes the situation that forced him to leave Pitt.
    - Offers and Requests, March-April 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Wyoming job opportunity, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Testimonial dinner, April 1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Government officials, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - General, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letter to Bill Stern, July 25, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Pittsburgh Athletic Association Sports Committee meeting, November 6, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Memorabilia, 4.
    The memorabilia in this subseries consists of event programs, poems written to Jock Sutherland, various certificates, a proclamation for the Brooklyn Dodgers, a draft of Sutherland's statement on political ambitions, and a copy of a check for Sutherland and the City of Pittsburgh, all of which comes from the same scrapbook as the correspondence in the series.
    - Certificates, programs, and other memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Football, 1930-1946; II.
  This series contains material related to football teams coached by Jock Sutherland. It includes preparatory materials, such as a playbook from one of his former players, as well as partial game programs. The Mississippi State contract in this series comes from the same disbound scrapbook as the material in Series I., where there is also a copy of the contract.
  - Pitt vs. Notre Dame football game program, October 25, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pittsburgh Steelers Grid Review page, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Charles "Red Dog" Fleming playbook, ca. 1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Nebraska scouting report, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Syracuse itinerary, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mississippi State blank contract, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Rose Bowl football, 1937
    Acquisition Information
    Gift of Dean "Pete" Wesley Oldham, Sr. and family.
- Press, 1936-1961; III.
  The press materials in the collection focus on Jock Sutherland's coaching career. They include a two-part Saturday Evening Post piece published in late 1939 discussing the resignation and aftermath. There are various magazines featuring interviews or generic articles on Dr. Sutherland and his coaching style. A later Saturday Evening Post article, written by Myron Cope and published almost 15 years after Dr. Sutherland's death, focuses on John Michelosen. Michelosen was the coach of the Panthers football team from 1955 to 1965, but had played for Sutherland and worked as an assistant for him. The article partly discusses Sutherland's influence on his former assistant. This series also includes a scrapbook of news clippings related to Sutherland's teams and his resignation from Pitt. The news clippings at the end of the series consist of loose articles from the scrapbook, organized by date.
  - Pittsburgh magazines, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Saturday Evening Post, October 28, 1939 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - Saturday Evening Post, November 4, 1939 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - The American Legion Magazine, November 1940 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Huddle football magazines, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Dapper Dan Dinner article, March 17, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Press release for "Jock Sutherland Day", 1954 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Saturday Evening Post, October 28, 1961 (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - News clipping scrapbook, 1937-1941 (Oversize 2, Volume 1)
  - Pittsburgh Press article, December 26, 1929 (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - News clippings, 1930s (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - News clippings, 1940s (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - Pittsburgh Press clip, March 15, 1959 (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
  - News clippings, undated (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
- Personal, IV.
  The Personal series of the collection contains material not related to football or Jock Sutherland's resignation. This includes photographs, event programs, memorabilia, and publications. The photographs include images of Sutherland in his naval uniform, as well as one of Malcolm Parcell painting his portrait.
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Travel (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Event programs (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Do You Know Football" article by Jock Sutherland, October 29, 1940 (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - Jock Sutherland: Architect of Men by Harry Scott, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)